<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Cushion</title>
    <link>http://cushionapp.com</link>
    <pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2014 18:36:42 +0000</pubDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-08-27</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-08-27</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2014 10:41:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-08-27</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m so close. I spent this last week putting the finishing touches on Cushion. The majority of them surrounded small UX issues that would’ve definitely arisen out of the beta. I figured I’d rather tackle them now and have a more solid product going into the initial testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-27-income-input.gif&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-27-income-input&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most overlooked UX issue involved the income input fields. Up until now, it was a simple number-based input. It would balk at any character other than a number (even commas and dollar signs) and there was no currency formatting. With a history of using awful currency-based input fields and pulling my hair out when it’s not perfect for the server, I decided to go out of my way to make this easy. Upon exiting the input field, it’ll run a validation function that strips out any character that doesn’t belong and then reformats it, inserting a dollar sign and any commas if we’re in the thousands. Also, if the amount includes cents, it will format that as well or leave it out if it’s an even dollar amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-27-success.gif&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-27-success&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I realized I didn’t show any sort of success message to indicate that a project or invoice was created, updated, or deleted. I started to design a full-width banner that would appear in the form, but decided to take a step back. You should be able to see this message at all times. If you’re scrolled out of the view of the banner area, that doesn’t mean you should miss it. Also, upon creating a new project, you’re taken to the edit view, so this message should carry across views. Because of this, I opted to pin the message at the top. It slides in when needed, remains visible in all scroll positions, and slides out after a couple seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-27-due-net.gif&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-27-due-net&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I tackled the longest overdue feature—a net option for invoices. I attempted to start on this feature a dozen times, but always gave up after a while to direct my attention elsewhere. The tricky part was positioning the form elements, so it felt like a natural flow from the issue date to due date to paid date. If I placed the custom due date input below the dropdown, it would look completely off, but if that custom input was hidden until selected, it wouldn’t look half-bad. I took a tally for common invoice nets to use, including “upon receipt”, and added the final option for a specific date. Eventually, this will default to your net preference, so you will only need to change it if the client has their own net.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-08-19</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-08-19</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2014 09:09:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-08-19</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Progress on Cushion has been amazing this past week. I feel like I’m past the point of shaping with play-doh and now using a fine-tooth chisel. I spent the majority of the time cleaning up the app, adding all of the parts that you forego when quickly prototyping, like error messaging and loading indicators. Even though these additions aren’t glamorous, they smooth out the experience. This is no longer a prototype—it’s a real app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second half of the week was more exciting. After speaking with a fellow studiomate about what’s important for the scheduling timeline, I realized the top priority should be clarity. And, up until this point, the scheduling timeline has been anything but clear. My mistake was trying to represent timeframes with bars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-19-old-timeline.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-19-old-timeline&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, this makes no sense. With a bar, you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have a start and an end, but they tell you nothing besides the start and end. What if I want to know if the project is ongoing? On top of that, there’s next to no information in between. Down the line, I’m certain we’ll need room for milestones and, potentially, other symbols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of a sudden, these bars started feeling like they represented a value other than time, especially when it came to invoices. An invoice that dragged on for months felt like a big-paying invoice. A project that spanned half the year but only required one day a week looked just like a full-time project. This lack of clarity became a real problem, to the point where I didn’t trust the visual. I had to spend a minute translating it before I could react and notice any valuable information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right when I was ready to leave for the day, I decided to quickly try out an idea. I scrapped the bars and started fresh. I tried to imagine a scheduling timeline without any history of what I have designed so far. Since it pertains dates and timespans, it should use dots and lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-19-estimated-actual.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-19-estimated-actual&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dots will represent the dates. For projects, this currently includes the estimated start/finish dates and actual start/finish dates. For invoices, the issue date, due date, and paid date. Estimated dates shouldn’t carry the same weight as the actual dates because they’re not confirmed, so any estimated dates will have a different style—an outlined circle. Then, any actual date will be a solid fill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-19-hide-estimated.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-19-hide-estimated&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This felt like a lot of dots. Then I realized we could imply the existence of the estimated dates through the style of the line. If a project starts late, the line from the estimated start date to the actual start date should be a lighter version of the working line. That alone tells what we want to know, but then we can show the specific dates upon hovering the project. This way, we can establish an overall timeline UX of “hover to show more information”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-19-future-project.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-19-future-project&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiding the estimated dates outside of hover also helps us when it comes to future projects. With no actual dates, these future projects are represented by only a light line—clearly showing that a project spans that timeframe, but it hasn’t been anchored with the weight of actual dates. Now there’s an obvious difference between a past project and a future project. But, what about current projects?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the previous bar design, we had no clear way of knowing which projects you were actively working on or which invoices were in the pipeline. I wanted to be able to look at the timeline and immediately know how many projects were active and which ones. With this new design, I introduced a new element—an arrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-19-active-project.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-19-active-project&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any project or invoice that spans the current date, an arrow will appear on that line. If a project has started, the line up until that arrow will be solid to show that you’ve actively worked on it up until now. The line after the arrow will remain lighter to indicate that you haven’t worked through that time yet, but it can potentially span that far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An arrow was the first thing that came to mind as a way of showing activity and it worked right off the bat. I can clearly distinguish these projects from the others and I don’t need a label because it pointing in the direction of time is all we need to get the point across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-19-dragged-project.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-19-dragged-project&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For projects that drag on, I reclaimed the hash pattern from the previous design. I still think it works with this new look as long as it’s the only place where we use a hash pattern. Also, like before, the pattern animates if an invoice is currently late. The movement is subtle enough to instill a sense of urgency, but won’t send you into panic mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous post, I touched on a new tooltip design for the scheduling timeline, showing more useful information than just a client/project label. With this new design, I decided to take it a step further and show even more. Since we’re now working with several new elements—dots, lines, and arrows—we could utilize all three of these to tell us more about projects and invoices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-19-estimated-finish-tooltip.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-19-estimated-finish-tooltip&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For dots, show the date that it represents and reiterate whether it’s estimated or not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-19-dragged-tooltip.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-19-dragged-tooltip&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For lines, indicate the duration of the line and what it represents—early, late, drag, active, etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-19-active-date-tooltip.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-19-active-date-tooltip&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for arrows, simply show that a project or invoice is active as of the current date. These new details help in revealing the additional information you would want to know, but it also keeps us from needing an additional key to reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-19-new-timeline.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-19-new-timeline&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After using the new scheduling timeline design for the past few days, I feel so much more confident and on top of things. I honestly can’t believe I even considered the previous design in the first place, but at least I know I’m making progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-08-11</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-08-11</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2014 09:43:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-08-11</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This last week, I focused primarily on the Cushion backend. In working locally on the app, I realized that it was becoming sluggish—especially on pages with a lot of content. I’ve been building this app with progress in mind, so I haven’t been as considerate as I should be. I query the database far too often and calculate the results in Ruby when it could all be done in the database. Because of this, performance issues are apparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a single request to retrieve a list of projects uses a single query for the projects, but then three additional queries for each project to grab the sum of its invoices. With my current personal data, this resulted in nearly 150 queries just to pull down my projects! Not good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew this would happen when I wrote the code because, at the time, I just needed it to work. I’m being a responsible dev and using test-driven development for the backend, so in order for the tests to pass, they just need the correct result. Now that I’m further along, however, I also need the code to perform well. Luckily, I can go back and fine-tune the code, knowing that my tests are in place to double-check that it still works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting up to speed with PostgreSQL, I realized just how much I could do in the database rather than in Ruby—apparently, much more than I imagined. I started by focusing on those invoices sums—paid income, unpaid income, and relative estimated income. The first two are straightforward—just paid invoices and unpaid invoices—but the last one is trickier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every project has an estimated income, which is a ballpark amount that this project could potentially bring in. It’s not a guarantee that you’ll reach that amount, nor is it a guarantee that it will &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; bring in that amount. It’s just a figure to give you an idea. With this figure, however, we can do some interesting things, like seeing how close or far off you were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we take the estimated income for a project and subtract the sum of its invoices, we can see the actual income relative to the estimated amount. As you’re working on the project, this can be useful for seeing how much is potentially remaining, if it’s capped-off at that amount. Or, if you’re working hourly without a cap, you  can see how much more you’ve made than originally anticipated. Hopefully, you fall in the latter end of this example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-11-client-budget.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-11-client-budget&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrapped up projects and moved up the chain to clients. For clients, I have these sums of income as well, but on a wider scale, combining the sums of each client’s projects. This is useful in seeing which clients bring in the most (in case you need to spread out your income streams) and which clients owe you the most (revealing a red flag going forward).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also have a lot of data to play with in regards to scheduling. Since every project has both estimated and actual start dates and end dates, I’ve been able reveal projects that start late or drag on too long. This is useful enough on the project level, but if we take a step back and group the projects by client, we can learn a lot about client tendencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-11-client-schedule.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-11-client-schedule&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, instead of sums, we can calculate averages. The three main columns represent the average duration, delay and drag of clients. With them, we can expose a lot. If a client consistently feeds you only small scope projects, you can know with confidence whether you can fit them in an open slot in your schedule. On the cautionary side, we can use average delay and drag to question whether you should still work with this client or just account for the delay and drag when planning the next gig with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-08-11-tooltips.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-08-11-tooltips&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also improved the schedule tooltip to provide written details of what you’re looking at rather than forcing you to do the math—you can now point to a specific segment of a bar and see what it represents. For clients and projects, these segments include the delay, drag, duration and estimated duration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under invoices, using the dates assigned to each (issued, due, and paid), the segments represent how early an invoice was paid, how late an invoice was paid (more realistic), how long an invoice took to get paid, and how long until an invoice is due.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these new tooltips in place, I feel like I’m going in a really good direction—taking useful data and making it easily accessible. Being able to see the data in table form is easy, but I’d rather provide the ability to interact with data in context.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-07-29</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-07-29</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2014 10:14:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-07-29</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past weekend, I focused on usability. My first stab on the layout of model forms was haphazard. While showing Cushion to a few people, I could see an obvious hesitation on where to start when creating a new project. All of a sudden, the user is presented with fields all over the place with no clear direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2014-07-29-new-form-layout.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-29-new-form-layout.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-29-new-form-layout&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believe it or not, I had a dream about the new layout and it’s the one I’m going with. Instead of letting the sections rest aside each other and reflow when needed, I just stack them and separate with dividers. Now, the sections actually represent the different views of Cushion (schedule and budget) and there’s a clear flow from top to bottom. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I was worried there would be too much negative space in the smaller sections, like budget, but it doesn’t feel as bad—especially if I end up going with a budget range instead of a single value. Also, this layout allows me to potentially include mini visuals for each section that provides more context than just input fields. Imagine the budget section including the average budget for your projects or the average budget for the client of that project. All of a sudden, you have a better idea of where to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with a revision of the layout, I’ve been working on improving the actual input fields. From the start, I chose HTML5’s native input types, thinking these would take care of a ton of extra work in the early stages. Unfortunately, some of the native input types, like &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;input type=&amp;#39;date&amp;#39;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, are cemented in ugly (can’t be styled) and don’t even work in common browsers like Safari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-29-color-picker.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-29-color-picker&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first input type I tackled was the color picker. I took a page from my buddies at &lt;a href=&quot;http://friendsoftheweb.com/&quot;&gt;Friends of the Web&lt;/a&gt; with their &lt;a href=&quot;http://dayswork.co&quot;&gt;Dayswork&lt;/a&gt; app and provided a simple popover of suggested colors. I &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; color pickers on the web that mimic those in design tools like Photoshop—they assume everyone is a designer. With suggested colors, any one of them will look good, and in most cases, you won’t need to use it because your client already has an established color. Considering this, the color picker is more of an easy way to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-29-date-picker.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-29-date-picker&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I addressed the date picker. For this, I wanted a design that is both useful and obvious to navigate—it should also have a couple Cushion-specific features that support the reasoning behind going custom. For instance, if the date is part of a range, the dates within the range should highlight to indicate that. Also, for validation purposes, you shouldn’t be able to pick a finish date that comes before the range’s start date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-29-color-inheritance.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-29-color-inheritance&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In filling out the forms, I also realized how tedious the process felt. Because of this, I added value inheritance. Let’s say you create a new project, but it doesn’t necessarily call for a color other than its client’s. Before, you would need to re-enter your client’s color. Now, it defaults to using the client’s color unless specified otherwise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-29-inline-client-inheritance.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-29-inline-client-inheritance&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also works reversely for the inline client creation. If you create a new project and set its color, the inline client will inherit that color by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, client and project symbols are now auto-generated with the ability to override them. This means if you create a new client named “Vandelay Industries”, its symbol will be “VI” by default, but you could overwrite it to something like “VanInd” if you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These recent updates have me incredibly excited to get Cushion in the hands of others as soon as possible. I know most of them are unnecessary for an initial beta release, but I want this app to be a joy to use from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-07-24</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-07-24</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2014 08:37:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-07-24</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been contemplating not mentioning this just yet because I don’t want it to seem like I’m ready to launch the beta, but… Cushion is now online. This past weekend, after great pressure from my wife (also a freelancer), I decided to set up everything needed to get Cushion working on a server. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew this would be a challenge, as it always is, but I wanted to get it out of the way early, so that everything I change from now on will need to work in production, avoiding any last-minute surprises. Also, it helps me establish a better process for updating the app, through the use of continuous integration and an asset pipeline that keeps compiled code outside of the dev branch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with all the deployment setup, I’ve integrated a few helpful services for performance metrics, exception tracking, and user analytics. As I progress with Cushion, I’ll rely on these services to fine-tune the app along the way. Everything is also wired to my personal Slack room, so I’m alerted of any issues as they happen. I want to get this app right from the start and this extra preparation will go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the beta, I don’t have a definite date in mind, but it’s sooner than later. I have a short list of crucial items to tackle, then all of the payment and legal stuff. As a reminder, the beta is paid in order to support early development and encourage users to provide real feedback. I’ve been a part of far too many free betas that attract countless stagnant users because there’s no incentive or motivation to consistently test the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in taking part in the beta, &lt;a href=&quot;/&quot;&gt;sign up&lt;/a&gt; to be notified.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSL Service</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/expenses/ssl-certificate-service</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 18:11:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/expenses/ssl-certificate-service</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSL Certificate</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/expenses/ssl-certificate</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 18:10:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/expenses/ssl-certificate</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web App Database</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/expenses/web-app-database</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 18:10:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/expenses/web-app-database</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web App Server</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/expenses/web-app</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 18:08:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/expenses/web-app</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-07-21</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-07-21</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 15:06:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-07-21</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After rethinking the project schedule timeline, I applied the same style to the invoice schedule timeline. With projects, we track the start and end dates to reveal if a project starts late or drags on too long. With invoices, we track when an invoice is paid compared to its due date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at scheduling, invoices differ from projects in that invoices can’t start late—its “start date” is when you issue it, and I hope you wouldn’t be late in sending an invoice! From the issue date, however, we can track how long it takes for the client to pay, revealing if they are early or late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-21-future-invoice.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-21-future-invoice&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-21-into-invoice.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-21-into-invoice&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you create an invoice, the bar is lightly hatched to indicate that window of time. As you progress into that window, the bar starts to fill solid up until the current date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-21-early-invoice.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-21-early-invoice&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an invoice is paid early (ha!), the bar is solid from the issue date to the pay date, but uses a very light hatching from the pay date to the due date. This way, you can easily see how early an invoice has been paid. Hopefully, your timeline will be full of invoices paid early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-21-late-invoice.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-21-late-invoice&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-21-still-late-invoice.gif&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-21-still-late-invoice&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the more common scenario, a client is late to pay. In this situation, if the invoice has been paid, the bar uses a thick hatching, identical to the one used on a project that dragged on. If, however, the client still hasn’t paid, the thick hatching will animate to emphasis that it is both late &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; unpaid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before wrapping up, I should note that none of these patterns are set in stone. Now that I’m starting to take on client work again, I’m trying to move faster with Cushion, so these patterns are a start. I definitely plan to add a key to reference and fine-tune them after using it for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-07-15</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-07-15</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 10:46:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-07-15</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past month, I’ve been traveling a whole lot, which explains the gap in journal posts. I did have a few pockets of time to work on Cushion, but not enough solid progress to justify a new post. Now that I’m back and settled, it’s time to go full speed ahead again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main focus as of late is the scheduling side of the app. I’m bummed that I spent the majority of this time focusing on budgeting when scheduling is the more day-to-day view. If I went with scheduling first, I probably would’ve been able to ship a beta prior to adding budgeting. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-15-old-schedule-timeline-design.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-15-old-schedule-timeline-design&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading up this post, the scheduling timeline consisted of thick bars labeled with the project name. With ideal data, this looked fine, but as soon as I plugged in my real freelancing data, I could tell this wouldn’t work. At one point I was working on five websites at once because of delayed start dates and delayed deadlines. As you could imagine, these thick bars stacked five-high took up half the screen and were difficult to read at a glance. With the real data, I went back to designing and came up with a thinner, more legible look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-15-schedule-timeline-design.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-15-schedule-timeline-design&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the thickness change, I also had to completely rethink the indicator of delay (project starting late) and drag (project finishing late). In the first design, both were signified with the same look—a lighter fill of the project color. This looked fine if a project started late or dragged on too long, but if it did both, the bar became very confusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-07-15-schedule-bar.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-07-15-schedule-bar&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to use hatching, instead of transparency, to fix the problem. Since a delay means you’re not working on a project yet, a lighter hatching would make the delayed piece of the bar feel slightly removed from the solid, but still a part of it. With drag meaning you’re actively working on the project past its deadline, a heavier hatching would made it feel closer to the solid—the time in which you’re actively working within the estimated dates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this new design in place, the scheduling timeline is now legible at a glance, even using my real data. It’s been so helpful in preparation of my return to client work, telling me everything I need to know about the upcoming months and assuring me that I have a handle on future projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-06-15</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-06-15</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2014 14:31:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-06-15</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After a ton of work on the budgeting side of Cushion, I decided to step back and focus on scheduling. I met with a few more fellow freelancers and the verdict seems to be that scheduling is a day-to-day activity, whereas budgeting is done less often—maybe week-to-week. If this is the case, I definitely want to have scheduling from day one, so everyone could get some frequent use out of Cushion. A weekly-used app won’t cut it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-15-schedule-tabs.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-15-schedule-tabs&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The navigation for switching between the scheduling and budgeting views stumped me for a few days. With the model tabs as an established navigation on the app, I didn’t want to add anything that would compete too much. I decided to scrap the Cushion title in the top-left for now. With UI real estate becoming a premium in this app, that spot is much better suited for the view switcher—it also allows more views in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the positioning of the view tabs, I had difficulty deciding on a URL structure, since this completely flips the current one on its head. With these two views, essentially every page will have two pages—one for scheduling and one for budgeting. If you look at a project page, instead of &lt;code&gt;/projects/:id&lt;/code&gt;, it would be &lt;code&gt;/projects/:id/schedule&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;/projects/:id/budget&lt;/code&gt;. This makes complete sense, but for some reason, it didn’t seem like the clear answer at first. I started thinking of what &lt;code&gt;/projects/new&lt;/code&gt; would be, since it currently shows the budgeting timeline. Would it now show both scheduling and budgeting, or neither?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-15-schedule-coded-vs-mockup.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-15-schedule-coded-vs-mockup&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scheduling timeline layout has been designed from the start of the app, but now that I needed to code it, a new challenge arose. Positioning a bunch of rectangles in a mockup is easy—the positioning logic is executed by the designer. With code, the simplest layout could come with a few hurdles of its own. For the scheduling timeline, all projects should rest on the baseline if they fit. If a project overlaps another project, it should rest above it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2014-06-15-schedule-timeline.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-15-schedule-timeline.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-15-schedule-timeline&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this can’t be done solely with CSS, like the budgeting timeline. After a few searches describing the layout I was after, I found a &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/bunkat/1962173&quot;&gt;chart&lt;/a&gt; that depicted the basic idea. It’s called a “swim lane” and is often used in flow charts. Once I saw the code required, I realized that this layout is actually pretty simple. Since I have start and finish dates for each project, I can just check for overlaps with those dates—no need for hit-detection. If a project’s finish date comes after another project’s start date, but its start date comes before that project’s finish date, you have an overlap. Upon finding an overlap, simply use a new “lane” for that item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-15-actual-schedule.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-15-actual-schedule&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, I have two dates for each project—&lt;code&gt;started_on&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;finished_on&lt;/code&gt;. These represent the actual dates for when the project started and finished, not their planned dates, which is why I use the past-tense. The next step is to add two more dates for estimated start and finish dates. These will be set upon creating the project and represent the agreed upon dates with the client. When you start a project, you set its &lt;code&gt;started_on&lt;/code&gt; date and its &lt;code&gt;finished_on&lt;/code&gt; date upon completion, so we have something to diff against. These four dates will let you see which clients are late to start or which ones drag on too long. From there, I can then find trends in specific clients.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-06-05</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-06-05</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2014 13:56:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-06-05</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently sat down with a friend who has shown interest in Cushion since I first mentioned it. I gave her a demo, but we also set up an account for her and plugged in all of her data—clients, projects, and invoices. I was both amazed and thrilled that she would let me input her real data even after suggesting we use dummy data for privacy. I’m glad we used the real data because her data instantly revealed a dozen issues with the current version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-05-new-project-client.gif&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-05-new-project-client&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, she doesn’t have a single client with more than one project. This became a huge issue as we constantly needed to jump back and forth, creating a client, then creating a project. It felt uncomfortably redundant. Because of this, I added a &amp;ldquo;New client&amp;rdquo; option to the client dropdown in the project form. Selecting it adds a few extra fields to the form, so you can also create a client there with a single click. The input fields also use the project fields as default values, so you don’t need to set the same color twice if it’s the same as the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-05-timeline-divider.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-05-timeline-divider&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second major issue I discovered was sequential timeline items that shared the same color. It was difficult to see the edge between them, but also, smaller projects would easily be lost without a label. To fight this, I added a very thin, transparent line to the edge of each item. It’s dark enough to show a separation without too much contrast. Even though I’m a sucker for full fills of color, I actually love the look these lines provide. The timeline feels much more solid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-05-timeline-hover.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-05-timeline-hover&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the divider, I finalized the hover state of the timeline items for when a label collapses to its abbreviation. Prior, I would show a tooltip-like element above the item and call it a day, but after adding the divider line, I decided to dim the item behind the tooltip. With the smaller projects, this really makes it clear as to which project you are hovering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third and final problem I’ll point out is the timeline’s inability to handle tiny items. For example, if your timline is set up with a goal of $100,000 and you have an unpaid invoice of $100 for a friend project, it &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; show up as the tiniest of slivers. Unfortunately, a CSS border forces a minimum width of twice the border width, so a 4px border would make any item at least 8px wide. I got around this by using the CSS outline instead. It allows the same controls as border (except for sides), but doesn’t have a minimum width.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to have more in-person demos in the coming weeks, so I can find even more of these issues. It’s an incredibly valuable learning experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-06-03</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-06-03</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 09:59:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-06-03</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After living with the changes I made to the timeline, I tweaked it a bit more. When a project is selected and the other projects fade in opacity, I also fade their colors to make the selected project pop even more. I had a problem with not being able to distinguish the selected project from the others with certain colors, but now it couldn’t be clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-03-timeline-fade.gif&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-03-timeline-fade&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started creating views for project lists, so you can create additional buckets. I haven’t pinned down the default lists yet, but there will most likely be three for active projects, potential gigs, and completed ones. I will personally add at least two more for pending projects (confirmed, but haven’t started) and dormant projects (active, but waiting on the client).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2014-06-03-list.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-03-list.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-03-list&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since lists deal with the project model, but don’t belong as a top-level tab, it’s tough to decide where to link to them. Right now, you can click a list header and it will take you to that list view, but what if I want a view for repositioning them? I’m almost certain I don’t want a separate view for that since we already have the projects view that is grouped by list, but there’s a chance something might come up. 
Also, regarding the repositioning of lists, is it drag-and-drop, a select menu, or move-up/move-down arrows? I’m a fan of drag-and-drop since it’s the most intuitive and relates to the physical world, but on a scale like this, where lists could span the entire screen, it wouldn’t be a good fit. Arrows would most certainly feel redundant if you need to move a list from the bottom to the top, not to mention the duplicate API requests. A select menu is probably best for now, unless I end up with a table view for lists, which would make drag-and-drop easier to implement and use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been feeling really good about where I am with Cushion, so I took a minute to plug in my real data from this current year. It’s enlightening to see how everything looks when all the data is familiar. Surprisingly, I find the individual project views to be incredibly valuable. It allows me focus on the current project and easily see the status of its invoices—I was even able to spot one that was long overdue! On past projects, the individual view gives me a sense of its history and impact on the year. I can weigh a project’s required effort with its actual return to see which ones were worth the late nights and which ones weren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just the beginning of what I can do with this data. I have so many more ideas that I can’t wait to try out. If anything specific would be useful for you, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/cushionapp&quot;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-06-01</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-06-01</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2014 11:40:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-06-01</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-01-no-modals.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-01-no-modals&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made a lot of progress this weekend regarding the overall feel of Cushion. The change I’m happiest with is the move away from modals. At first, I used modals for the project creation view. I did this because I didn’t have enough data, at the time, to warrant an entire page—bad design reasoning, I know. A benefit of the modal, however, is to keep the user in the projects view, so you can add a several projects and see them populate the tables. After using Cushion more, I realized this wouldn’t be a common interaction, unless a user adds all of their projects upfront.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-01-new-project.gif&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-01-new-project&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I moved the new project view to its own page and everything started coming together. The form is the same as the one in the edit view, so I can simply reuse that code. The beauty of the change, though, is that transition from creating a new project to its project page—it’s seamless. Since the layout is pretty much the same, the invoice tables simply appear below the form and we’re good to go. A next step would be to add a button for creating invoices. Eventually, I’d like to add the option to point your project to your invoicing service of choice, so it automatically pulls in invoices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-06-01-timeline.gif&quot; alt=&quot;2014-06-01-timeline&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding transitions, the timeline now fades between views, so you can see how each view relates to the previous one. The current timeline views all share a similar structure, exposing more detail as you move from invoices to clients to projects. Then, when you click into a project, the unrelated projects will fade to make the selected one more prominent (hat tip to &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/tealtan&quot;&gt;Allen Tan&lt;/a&gt; for the suggestion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, I’m going to build out all of the create, edit, and delete views for the other models and have a pretty usable version by the end of the week. Regarding the schedule, I’m way ahead of my goal of a beta by the end of the month. I’m certain there will be a ton of last-minute items to tackle before I can share Cushion, but I like where we are.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-05-28</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-05-28</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2014 13:04:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-05-28</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent the majority of the day working on the individual project page. At first, I was on the fence about whether to show a form for editing the project’s fields or just display its details with the option to edit. I went with the former because I hate extra steps. If a user clicks into a project, they probably don’t want to just see the same info they’ve seen elsewhere—they want to edit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2014-05-28-project.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-05-28-project.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-05-28-project&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the form, I added two tables for that project’s paid and unpaid invoices. With this, the project page is essentially a filter of the other views. The user can focus on that one project without being distracted by all the other projects they might have going on. The timeline is also filtered to only show that project’s incomes and how they apply to the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-05-28-late-invoice.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-05-28-late-invoice&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also took a break from this page to add a small detail to the invoice table—a red highlight for late invoices. This will be very useful for being aware of them without the need of a scary, jarring alert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-05-28-symbols.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-05-28-symbols&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the timeline, I revisited the label view, adding a bit more logic to switch between showing a project’s symbol or its full name. If there’s not enough room for either, I hide both and rely on a hover if the user really needs to see the name. For the money, I’m considering reducing them from something like “$5,000” to “$5k” when narrower, but not entirely convinced—it could get messy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-05-27</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-05-27</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 09:21:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-05-27</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m making so much progress. I almost can’t sit still. Each night, I go to bed thinking about Cushion and wake up thinking about it. Needless to say, everything is going well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished the refactor of changing the Status model to List, which immediately feels clearer. Now you can have a list, or bucket, of projects and it doesn’t need to represent a status. I’m certain people will use Cushion much differently than I would have expected, so I don’t want to force too many workflows on them. I typically separate my projects into “Active”, “Pending”, “Potential”, and “Done”, but there are so many other possibilities, I might adopt a few more, like “Dormant”. This would represent any project that is blocked for one reason or another, so you don’t need to worry about it until they get back to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-05-27-estimated-income.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-05-27-estimated-income&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the income side of things, I added another column. Prior, I had two columns—“Paid” and “Unpaid”. These values were pulled from a sum of the invoices for a given project, so you know how much has been made versus how much is pending. But what about when you start a project and have a general idea of how much it will bring in? That should be represented on the timeline as well, so I added “Estimated”. This is a ballpark figure represented by a single column in the database, so when you create a project, you just give it a number. At some point, it would be nice to be more granular with the estimate and comparing detailed estimates against actual outcomes, but this works for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This weekend, I spoke to a few friends who would be prime users and over the next month, I’m going to continue doing more research along these lines. It’s incredibly fascinating hearing other freelancers or design studio owners talk about their needs—especially when most of them aren’t covered by the plethora of existing services. This makes me even more hopeful for Cushion. I know it fits the bill for me, but it’s reassuring when I hear from others that they need it, too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-05-18</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-05-18</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2014 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-05-18</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I realize it has been over a week since my last entry and for good reason—frustration over the front-end framework. I’ve been hopping around, trying each one out, hoping to find a good fit. As soon as I think I found one, however, a deal breaker would surface and I would have to look elsewhere. I’m confident with the one I’ve been using over the last week, Backbone, as it fits my needs without any magic. I don’t want to waste any more time on this, so let’s move on to new thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning, I’ve considered changing the “Status” model to “List”. While using the prototype, I constantly finding myself wondering about the status—it feels so specific. If I were to simply rename it to “List”, it could take on new meanings and use-cases. It could then also be used for clients. A client status doesn’t really make sense if you have a project status, but with lists, you could group them however you like, and that could be reflected visually in the timeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might be getting ahead of myself with this, so I’ll keep it in mind of the next few days, but stay the course, so I can make some real progress. I feel like I’ve been staring at the same view for the past few weeks. By the end of the month, I want to be able to use Cushion with real projects and get some use out of it. Then, I can tinker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a related note, my goal has been to reach beta by the end of June. I think it’s achievable now that I have the stack in order, but I have a few concerns based on previous betas I’ve held or been a part of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it will be a paid beta. This helps in two ways—funding the app early, so I can continue working on it, and ensuring that the beta testers are serious and proactive. I’ve “beta tested” countless apps before and I put that in quotes for a reason. I beta tested in the sense that I signed up, tinkered for less than an hour, then didn’t use it again or provide feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Cushion beta, I want to start with a small group of users that I chat with often and rely on for the early decisions. I don’t want to feel like I’m bothering people with surveys or unwanted emails—this core group should expect it. I’ll send out a few questions each week and make myself available for discussions. It should be a fun experience that makes you feel like you’re really contributing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Cushion will be released incrementally, both for the beta and for the public app. It’s overwhelming to open the flood gates on day one—I’d rather grow in more manageable waves. The beta will start with a few dozen, then grow by a few dozen as it’s improved and when it demands more feedback. When Cushion is public, I’ll grow it in larger increments, but still cap the user count to an amount I can handle on my own. Only when I can grow a team will I grow the user count past what’s manageable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-05-06</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-05-06</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 11:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-05-06</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent most of the day staring at the screen, thinking. I flipped back and forth between the prototype and the design flats, figuring out what to work on next. The timeline section at the top hadn’t received much love, so I focused my attention there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2014-05-06-timeline.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-05-06-timeline.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-05-06-timeline&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The timeline is terrifying because it’s going to be a challenge to make it look good with real data. Based on my personal usage, it looks great, but only because I’ve been lucky—working on projects that make it look great. Once I added random data that scales between very low-budget projects to very high-paying projects, it turned into fright night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem is the width of each project and the logic that will go into showing or hiding the label. For freelancers who work on dozens of projects in a given month, like illustrators, projects will probably never be wide enough to show the inner label. Because of this, I’ll rely on the color of the bar and maybe show a tooltip label on hover. As an in-between measure, I could also add a “symbol” attribute. This way projects like Kramerica’s Oil Bladder would show “K” for the client and “OB” for the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also plan on having multiple zoom views for the timeline, so projects won’t always feel so crunched. The initial view shows the entire year, but you’ll be able to focus in on a given month or quarter. This will spread out the projects and probably be the more common view for freelancers who work on shorter-term projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2014-05-06-timeline-days.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-05-06-timeline-days.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-05-06-timeline-days&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The timeline section has so much potential because I can build so many different views into it. The early designs included everything from planning projects per days and visualizing overlap to grouped income by project type. I can’t wait to flesh it out some more and continue fine-tuning it based on real data. I’m determined to make the final result really solid and able to handle any use-case.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014-05-05</title>
      <link>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-05-05</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 11:03:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Jonnie Hallman</author>
      <guid>http://cushionapp.com/journal/2014-05-05</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After creating the invoice model and provided it with its own table section, I started integrating it into the rest of the sections. The projects section now has a column for paid and unpaid invoice amounts as well as a footer under each table for the sums. For the paid/unpaid attribute, I researched a few of the services I plan to integrate with and looked at how they represent this in their invoice model. Each one has a status for invoices, with half a dozen options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getharvest.com&quot;&gt;Harvest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;open, partial, draft, paid, unpaid, past due&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://freshbooks.com&quot;&gt;Freshbooks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;disputed, draft, sent, viewed, paid, auto-paid, retry, failed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dayswork.co&quot;&gt;Dayswork&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;unresolved, paid, uncollectable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, like with the project statuses, no one can agree on a set of common statuses to use, so we have a long list of unique ones per service. Since these are all services where you can create invoices and track them on a granular level, they need the specific statuses, like draft, viewed, etc. I have absolutely no plans for invoice creation in Cushion, so I have it easier when it comes to statuses. What I really want to know is whether or not an invoice has been paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2014-05-05-invoices.png&quot; alt=&quot;2014-05-05-invoices&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally, I created a boolean &lt;code&gt;paid&lt;/code&gt; attribute and used that as an indicator. After separating the invoices section into two tables, “paid” and “unpaid”, I noticed this boolean wouldn’t suffice—I needed more relevant data. For instance, in the paid table, I no longer need the “due” column—I’d much rather see when invoices were paid. Considering this, I changed the &lt;code&gt;paid&lt;/code&gt; attribute to a date, called &lt;code&gt;paid_on&lt;/code&gt;. This gives me the date on which the invoice was paid and an easy indicator of whether it was paid or not (true if the date is set).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m excited about the invoice portion of the app because every service provides so much useful data. For now, I plan to condense it into something easier to digest, but down the road, there is so much I can do with it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
